Finding Aid for United Church of Christ. Southwest Association (Mich.) records, 1849-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
United Church of Christ. Southwest Association (Mich.) records 1849-1968
United Church of Christ. Southwest Association (Mich.)
86916 Ba 2
Formerly known as the Kalamazoo Congregational Association (1849-1938) and the Kalamazoo Association of Congregational-Christian Churches of Michigan (1938-1963). Correspondence, minutes, directories, membership records, and records of some churches in the association.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by Mrs. Loren Phelps 5097 in 1979.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Kalamazoo Congregational Association was formed May 8, 1849. Previously, in May 1840, the Eastern Association and Conference had been organized for the southeastern portion of the state; in 1841, the Marshall Conference (later Olivet Conference) was established, followed by the Jackson Conference in May 1842. Then, on October 11, 1842, the Congregational churches of Michigan were organized into a State Association. The Kalamazoo Association represented churches of western Michigan, including those in Allegan, St. Joseph, South Haven, Battle Creek, and Kalamazoo among others.
The record group includes minutes of annual meetings, correspondence, communications between the Association and the local churches, and other records documenting the organization and activities of the Association. Most of the records pertain to the period before the merger with the Evangelical and Reformed Church.
The series in the record group include: Record books; General correspondence; Church files; Other Records; and Conference Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Kalamazoo Association of Congregational Christian Churches of Michigan.; United Church of Christ. Southwest Association (Mich.)
- Record books
  - Minutes of annual meetings 1849-1881 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of annual meetings 1882-1937 also includes treasurer's report, 1882-1900 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of annual meetings 1938-1964 (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's Book 1899-1927 (Box 1)
    (includes church tax and membership record)
  - Constitution and membership record circa 1882-1938 includes catalogs of ministers, churches, and licentiates (Box 1)
    (this volume partially indexes the association's bound records)
- General correspondence
  - 1945-1963, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - 1964-1968, 5 folders (Box 2)
- Church files
  - Alamo Community Congregational Church 1947-1960 (Box 2)
  - Allegan. First Congregational Church 1950 (Box 2)
  - Athens. First Congregational Church 1958-1965 (Box 2)
  - Baroda. First Congregational Church 1892 (Box 2)
  - Battle Creek. First Congregational Church 1942-1964 (Box 2)
  - Coloma. First Congregational Church 1943-1966 (Box 2)
  - Dowagiac. Federated Church 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Eau Claire. Community Congregational Church 1948-1958 (Box 2)
  - Galesburg. First Congregational Church 1940-1965 (Box 2)
  - Lawrence. First Congregational Church 1958-1966 (Box 2)
  - Mattawan. First Congregational Church 1955-1966 (Box 2)
  - Otsego. First Congregational Church 1964 (Box 2)
  - Portage. Congregational Church 1963 (Box 2)
  - St. Joseph. First Congregational Church 1938-1966 (Box 2)
  - Sawyer. Christian United Church of Christ 1943-1965 (Box 2)
  - South Haven. First Congregational Church 1949-1965 (Box 2)
  - Tekonsha. Union Church 1963-1966 (Box 2)
  - Texas. Congregational Church 1951-1959 (Box 2)
  - Watervliet. Plymouth Congregational Church 1941-1963 (Box 2)
  - Assorted churches (Box 2)
  - Letters to Churches
    - 1950-1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961-1968 (Box 2)
- Other records
  - Advisory Board, minutes and records
    - 1937-1952 (Box 2)
    - 1953-1964 (Box 2)
  - Annual and Semi-annual. Meetings
    - 1936-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1968 (Box 2)
  - Committees
    - Executive committee, minutes 1960-1968 (Box 2)
    - Christian Education committee 1963-1968 (Box 2)
    - Lay life and work committee 1963-1965 (Box 2)
    - Our Christian World Mission Committee 1964-1967 (Box 2)
    - Social Concern and Extension and Renewal committees 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - Ministry, Committee on
      - Ministry Committee minutes 1959-1967 (Box 2)
      - Ordination papers (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1948-1968, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Miscellanea (Box 2)
  - Constitution and bylaws 1902-1964 (Box 2)
  - Financial records
    - 1949-1963 (Box 2)
    - 1964-1969 (Box 2)
  - Ministers and churches 1948-1968 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Officers and committees 1954-1968 (Box 2)
  - Paper circa 1892 "The Kalamazoo Association-Past and Present" (Box 2)
  - Paper 1948 "In Celebration of the 100th Annual Meeting of the Kalamazoo Association of Congregational Churches" (Box 2)
- Conference Materials
  - 1905 (Box 2)
  - 1957-1968 (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea (Box 2)